<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvonders of this windie winter By terrible stormes and tempests, to the losse of liues and goods of many thousands of men, women and children. The like by sea and land, hath not beene seene, nor heard of in this age or the world.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15677</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25949</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103315</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839072</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839072</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3468</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15677)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3468)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1225:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvonders of this windie winter By terrible stormes and tempests, to the losse of liues and goods of many thousands of men, women and children. The like by sea and land, hath not beene seene, nor heard of in this age or the world.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Eld for Iohn Wright, and are to bee sold at his shop in Christ-Church dore,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1613]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ (-A1) B-C⁴ (-C4).</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with imprint "London. Printed for Ioseph Hunt and are to be sold by Iohn Wright, at his shop neere Christ-Church dore. 1613.".</note>
                  <note>With woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Lamentable reports, of this windie winter.</note>
                  <note>Print blurred and show-through; title page stained; imprint date cut away (supplied by British Library Catalogue).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Storms --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Winter storms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3468:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3468:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The VVonders of this windie winter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By terrible ſtormes and tempeſts, to the loſſe of liues and goods of many thouſands of men, women and children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like by Sea and Land, hath not beene ſeene, nor heard of in this age of the World.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON. printed by <hi>G. Eld,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Wright,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop near Chriſt-Church dore. 1619.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3468:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3468:2"/>
            <head>Lamentable reports of this <hi>windy Winter, contayning the wonderfull,</hi> and ſtrange miſchances happened by tempeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtormes of winde and weather, in theſe <hi>three forepaſſed months of</hi> October, Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and <hi>December,</hi> with part of <hi>Ianuary.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this old, and laſt age of the World, we yeer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behold the ſtrange alterations of times &amp; ſeaſons, and therein, wee are put in minde of Gods anger purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt vs, by many variable and vnuſiall acſidents, happening in theſe our latter daies, to mooue ſinful mankind to repentance and new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, which if we with the inward eyes of vnderſtanding, conſider of in remorſe of conſience, we ſhall finde that the heauy hand of heauen is lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed violently vpon vs, as wel in taking away our great hope, and earthly ioy (<hi>Henry</hi> our Royall Prince) as theſe our late lamentable miſchances by winde and waters added to our ſorrowes, giuing vs an outward calamity to our inward griefes, Heauen, let vs not thinke amiſſe, if we ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly
<pb facs="tcp:3468:3"/> ſay it is for our ſins &amp; tranſgreſſions, and that they be forerunners of Gods reſtles indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt vs; God of his great pitty be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto vs and grant vs ſpeedy repentance.</p>
            <p>We haue within theſe few yeers, as well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this our natiue countrey of England as in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine nations, beene moſt grieuouſly ſtroken with the bitter blaſts of powerfull greatnes, one while with the darts of death, as by plagues &amp; peſtilence, continuing long amongſt vs; another time by drie ſummers, and parching heates, droughts, &amp; ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſulphers drying vp the moyſtures of the earth, to cauſe barrenneſſe with ſcarcety, then fréezing and cold winters in more then vſuall extremity to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy vs; another time by floods and ouerflowings of waters breaking from the boundes of the Seas, in which mercileſſe element many hundreds haue pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and haue loſt both life and goods, as the weſt parts of England, in the yeere of our Lord, 1607. can ſufficiently witneſſe: Fierie leſſes, by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable burning of many Townes: ſtrange ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, by corruption of ayre: deare yeers, by ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of victuall, and ſuch like; all which be the conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming plagues of heauen, laid vpon the ſhoulders of the ſinfull world, a burthen ſo eaſeleſſe that no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe can come but by forgiueneſſe.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, deare countrie-men of England, let vs now call to preſent memory another powerfull ſcourge laide vpon vs, a daily calamity, theſe into long continuing windes and tempeſts, which theſe three forepaſſed Moneths hath, almoſt, euerie day and night affrighted vs with feare (as it were) ſhaking the foundations of the ground, with ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings in our eares like thunder, the terrible blaſts whereof hath with ſuch extremity continued, that they haue made many fearefull repreſentations of
<pb facs="tcp:3468:3"/> the dreadfull trumpets of Gods wrath loudly blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en from heauen to the earth, the ſurie thereof (by his diuine ſufferance) hath mightily troubled (both ſea and land) the Inhabitants of many countries, but eſpecially our natiue Kingdome, to the leſſe of many thouſands which haue loſt both life and goods in this mortall miſerie: therefore let vs ſay with the Wiſe-men; Happie is hee that is ſo prouided in life, that no kinde of death is ſodaine vnto him, and let vs with patience take our deſerued puiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for the ſmalleſt breath of Gods noſtrils, like a whirle-wind, can deſtroy the tottering globe of the whole earth.</p>
            <p>It is with ſorrow remembred, and with griefs reported in the Citie of London, euen vpon the roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Exchange, the honourable and worthy meeting place of Merchants; that within theſe three fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed Moneths of October, Nouember, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember, the deuouring gulfes of the ſea hath ſwallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp aboue two hundred ſaile of ſhips, as well of our owne Countrey, as of neighbouring Nations, with great ſtore of paſſengers, ſea-faring men, and owners of the ſame, aduenturing their deare liues in the managing of the aforeſaid ſhips, with all their goods, and marchandizes making for our countrey, all loſt; yea all, I ſay, in theſe three fore-paſſed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, hath béen loſt and drenched in the déep vaults of this watery world, a thing both lamentable and fearefull, that in ſo ſhort a time; nay, in a ſmall part of the yeare, euen in an inſtant, ſo many heauie miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanches ſhould happen, and ſo many worthy veſſels of aduenture miſcarrie, which had bin ſufficient (if good ſpeed had preuailed) to haue inricht a whole Citie and bettered a kingdome; but ſuch is the will of God and ſuch is his moſt iuſt indignation againſt vs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3468:4"/>
            <p>It moues my heart with remorſe, to think how many people are vndone hereby, and how that ſome few particular men ſhould ſuffer ſhip-wrack, and by one robuſtious tempeſt bee depriued of that which might haue benefitted thouſands, therfore he that will enter rightly into conſideration hereof muſt needes acknowledge the caſe lamentable and the ſorrow vnſpeakable.</p>
            <p>By certification from men of good accompt and calling, it is reported and knowne for truth, that in the month of October laſt, a fleet of foureteene ſayle of ſhips making from New-Caſtle towards Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, laden with ſea-coale and other commodities of thoſe parts, had their paſſage by the tyranny of the windes moſt vntimely ſtopt, and violently caſt into the Oceans wombe: in which ſhips there periſhed to the number of a hundred and fortie ſea-faring men, beſides other paſſengers, both of men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which at that time made their watery graues in the déepe ſea: This, Firſt ſtrooke feare into the hearts of people, which hath been ſince ſeconded with many more calamities, which lieth heauie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heart of the reporter.</p>
            <p>The narrow ſeas betwixt Douer and Calice can witnes many like miſhaps, for by letters ſent vnto diuers great perſonages of the land, it is apro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that vpon the coaſt of France, there hath been found floating, vpon the waters, in one weeke of fowle weather, aboue ſeauen hundred drowned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of diuers nations, as of Engliſh, Dutch, French, and Spaniſh, with parts and parcels of many ſplitted ſhips, with great ſtore of goods by the fury of the windes beat vpon the ſhoare, a ſight of ſorrow, and moſt lamentable to behold; it is not as yet nearely knowne what riches the ſea hath ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in theſe three aforeſayd monthes, nor what
<pb facs="tcp:3468:4"/> loſſes other Countries haue ſuſtained, I feare me, the tenth part is not diſcouered, for God in his high diſpleaſure, ſtill threatens vs with theſe long laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tempeſts, day by day ſending vs ſorrow vpon ſorrow, with hourely newes of ſhipwrackes and loſſes at ſea, the ſcattering of fléets by contrary winds and violent tempeſts, in one place ſhips caſt away laden with cloath, in another, veſſels of ſalt, ſome with one thing, ſome with another, all rich, and of too great a price to be thus ſodainly waſted to the benefit of no creature.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe vpon our Engliſh coaſts, more néere the Weſt parts hath béene caſt away, diuers other ſhips, comming from <hi>Spaine,</hi> where in one of them were knowne to be ſeuentéene paſſengers of good reconing and calling, and ſome of them cittizens of <hi>London,</hi> which were found dead floating on the waters, ſome vpon plankes of wood, péeces of maſtes and ſuch like, which the fury of the winde and weather had ſplitted and torne in ſunder, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt this drowned number (being a fight of great griefe) there was taken vp a woman, with a child cloſed to her breſt, as it were ſucking, alſo two other women, claſped together arme in arme, as it ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, dying in each others boſoms.</p>
            <p>It is alſo credibly reported, by the eye witneſſes of this woful accident, that vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Weſterne ſeas, néere to the coaſt of <hi>Corne-wal,</hi> a certaine ſhippe was diſcouered, euen ſuncke to the top of her maine maſt, with ſome fiue or ſixe ſaylers, remayning in the top eradle to ſaue their liues, but there eſcaping drowning by water, they were ſtarued to death with cold and want of food, and ſo found in a calme day by another ſhip aduenturing to preſerue them, oh pittiful report and full of heauineſſe.</p>
            <p>A number more of the like miſeries, hath lately
<pb facs="tcp:3468:5"/> happened by reaſon of theſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtious winds, but eſpetially to the ſea-men, &amp; ſuch as haue committed themſelues, their liues, &amp; eſtates to the mercies of wind &amp; weather, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom almoſt no other newes come, but reports of moſt dangerous eſcapes, terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhipwracks, with loſſe of life &amp; goods, the impoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing of marchants, the ſinking of ſhips and ſuch like: of which woful loſſes, many of our inhanſing extorſioners, makes profit, rayſing their merchant-like co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, with other wares to high rates and priſes, working a recouerable ſubſtance out of poore mens purſes, careleſſe of paſſed calamities, ob coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous deſiers, oh lamentable hearing, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearts of people are thus hardned. God in his high power, preuent their purpoſes, &amp; alay theſe great winds, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> call my weather may comfort vs, and ad a forward willingneſſe to al ſea aduenturers, to continue their wonted profeſſion, euen now (many of them) diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> countries benefits, by reaſon of theſe long continuing tempeſts. Many more ſubiects of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row preſent themſelues before vs, and fils our eares with loſſe vpon loſſe, to the heart griefes of all good minds, for this watery kingdome, this vnſatiſfied gulfe, hath claſped into her boſom, to the vndoing of many thouſands, a number of hoies, barks &amp; veſſels, ſuch as aduentured out for fiſh, herrings, oyſters &amp; ſuch ſea victual, into the North ſeas, and haue there ſuffered ſhipwrack, and diued the Oceans bottome paſt the recouery of man &amp; helpe of the world.</p>
            <p>It hath béen certified for a truth, to ſome of the greateſt ſtateſmen of the Land, that betwixt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelmas &amp; Chriſtmas laſt, the ſeas haue bereaued 7000. and od people of their liues and that at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and in the coaſt townes of <hi>England,</hi> néere the ſea ſide there are knowne to be fouretéene hundred ſea-faring mens widdowes, beſide fatherleſſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb facs="tcp:3468:5"/> &amp; children fatherleſſe. Therefore let al tender hearted people ſay, with me, that theſe thrée months haue bin times of heauineſſe, yea times of greateſt grief, when the owners of ſhips and the goods ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for which they haue labored many a long yéere, &amp; trauelled for in many a weary winter, to be thus in one tempeſt caſt away and loſt, and themſelues (though eſcaping life) with their wiues and children brought to pouerty: how can we choſe, but with eies of pitty, &amp; with teare-beſtained chéekes, being men, much more Chriſtians, but relent at our neighbors loſſes, and perticipate with them in mone.</p>
            <p>Let vs (oh my déere countrimen of <hi>England</hi>) make our petition to God, that he would alay this windy inſtrument of his wrath, &amp; al other his angers oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt vs for our ſinnes, and confeſſe that our tranſgreſſions euen ſtink in the noſtrels of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſty: he is merciful, and ſends vs dayly (as we ſee) examples both by Sea and Land to win vs from wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>If we caſt but our eies, vpon the City of <hi>London</hi> and the townes and villages neere vnto the ſame, we may behold the fury of his high offended power in witneſſing the ſpoiles of ſtately houſes, and the high turrets of great perſonages, by theſe vnruly winds defaced, and as it were, in their greateſt pride torne in ſunder.</p>
            <p>Looke vpon the dwellings of many worthy Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of this City, &amp; we ſhal ſee that God is angry, by the vnlooſing of theſe powerfull windes, and by ſuffering them terribly, is vncouer their ſtately Archytectures, vntopping their peiring pinickles, blowing downe whole ſides of houſes, yet for all this many of them are merciles, regarding no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all the ſtrangeneſſe of theſe accidents, nor the fearefulneſſe of theſe times and ſeaſons, but
<pb facs="tcp:3468:6"/> accounts them natural, common, and vſuall, more like vnto Atheiſts, then Chriſtians, but, oh you temporizing naturalliſts except you repent, full vials of Gods wrath wil be powred downe vpon your heads, and all your temporal purpoſes brought to nothing.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, let vs ſettle, before our eyes, and in our preſent remembrance, theſe following examples of Gods power, which with the breath of his mouth workes wonders, theſe following examples, I ſay, by theſe late tempeſtious winds done in diuers thiers of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; we ſhal think the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> marueilous: was it not a ſtrang accident that a flock of ſhéepe, belonging to a Farmer in <hi>Lincoln-ſhire,</hi> néere vnto the town of <hi>Boſton,</hi> named <hi>George Kidman,</hi> ſhould by the aforeſaid winds in one night, be driuen twenty miles and more, and then blown into a part of the ſea and there drowned, herein was not the winde powerful? yes, yes, ſo powerful, and ſtrong, that it euen confunds humain reaſon to conſider of.</p>
            <p>It is alſo reported by letters, directed to diuers Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> that in the ſame County of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> a heard of beaſts by violence of the wind and weather, this very laſt month of <hi>December,</hi> were driuen into a Fenny Marſh, and there moſt ſtrangely ſtifeled with durt and water, the owners of theſe beaſts, are certaine ſubſtancial yeomen, whoſe names, to cut off tedious diſcriptions, for this time I omit.</p>
            <p>The wind as we may wel vnderſtand is ſtrong &amp; vnreſiſtable, by ſom ſuppoſed to be a ſpirit, compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the world (by Gods ſuffera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) to work wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, but in my opinion it is an ayery inſtrument of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty, apointed by heauen for the vſe of Gods creatures, which brings vs many times much bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe, and purifies the earth from diuers
<pb facs="tcp:3468:6"/> corruptions, but at this time for our ſelues we haue been therewith much annoyed, as it hath here been deſcribed both by ſea and land; the violence thereof hath cauſed much hurt in diuers countries, by rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of waters, and beating in of the floods, and ſuch like; by which meanes Trauellers are hindred of their iourneies, and many thereby drowned by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturing.</p>
            <p>As for example, vpon the Wedneſday before Chriſtmas laſt, a man &amp; his wife riding ouer Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den-head bridge both vpon one horſe, by the fiercenes of the wind were blowne beſide, and there drowned both horſe and all, God be merciful vnto vs, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs from all ſuch like miſchances.</p>
            <p>The like miſhap befell in Nouember laſt, vnto two York-ſhire men, as it is verified by ſome Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the Innes of Court, and Chancery which knew the parties, the one of them a Tanner, named Francis Browne, the other a Clothier, called Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Smith, both dwelling in a Towne neere Wakefield ſide, called Therby; which two Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie-men falling out vpon ſmall occaſions, wilfully purpoſed to come vp to London, and there put their Cauſes of themſelues to the Lawes tryall: yet notwithſtanding came they vp together, where, in riding ouer a Bridge about Bedford-ſhire, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of their inward grudges, they were blowne both beſide into the Riuer; where, by the fiercenes of the windes they were moſt lamentably drowned, both horſe and men: and thus by ſodaine death en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their malice, to the feare and amazement of all ſuch as wel could witnes their enuious procedings; theſe, and ſuch like accidents may be feareful exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for the world to behold, eſpecially for rich-men, ſhewing to them the certaintie of life and goods ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the chaunces of death and fortune: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:3468:7"/> to the ſaying of a worthy Philoſopher.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Full little thinks the man at morning Sun,</l>
               <l>What hap to him befals ere day be done.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Therefore, let vs pray for good ſucceſſe in all our buſineſſes, guided and accompanied with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of heauen, and then no doubt but better chance will betide vs then theſe two malitious country-men had in their iourney.</p>
            <p>We haue yet more notice, (gentle Reader) of other ſorrowfull diſcourſes to relate of, which well may beget your ſad entertainment, and poſſeſſe your hearts with remorſe, for they be ſtrange and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and in the eare of the hearer full of dole.</p>
            <p>Let vs now paſſe into the middle parts or ſhires of England, and tel what miſchances there hapned, the three ſhires of Warwick, Leceſter, and North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton (I meane) where the Inhabitants thereof, with ſtacks and ricks of hey, peaze, and beanes do vſually (in winter times) feed and fatten ſhéep, and ſwine, thoſe country-men (the more is my griefe to report) by theſe aforeſayd tempeſts haue endured much loſſe, for many of their ſhéep and ſwine haue béen ſmothered vnder the ricks and ſtackes blowne down by the winds, beſides barns and ſtables with many huſbandly houſes torne and vncouered of thatch by the ſame: Likewiſe the dwellings of yo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, farmers, &amp; laboring plow-men in thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, haue bin ouerturned with the rage of this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous commander, wel may we therfore (if we conſider al theſe things arightly) call this the blacke fatall winter of miſhaps, in which time many bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens of ſorrow be laid vpon our contry, God be our comfort: for alas, alas, the aforeſaid raging windes in diuers other ſhires of England haue beaten down a number of houſes, diſpearcing the ſubſtance of the poore owners, where many of them periſhed in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing
<pb facs="tcp:3468:7"/> their ſubſtance from the fal of their houſes.</p>
            <p>Yet let vs make no queſtion but that God is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, and hath plauged ſom few with the loſſe of life and goods, (if it be poſſible) to call others to amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life: Therefore aboue all things let vs take héed, that long eſcapes of puniſhment, or the vaine hopes of long life do not delude vs, and make vs ſtill run into our ſins without hope of returne.</p>
            <p>But to our lamentable narration againe, many the like ſtrange euents, fell out in other countries and parts of the kingdome; as for example, 2. or 3. ſhéep-kéepers in a part of Saliſbury Plaine, in the weſt of England can witnes, who in a moſt tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtious day, as it is wel knowne in the beginning of December, betook themſelues to a Cabin or Caue in the ground for ſhelter (as there be many in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) where, by the furiouſnes of the tempeſtious winds then blowing in greateſt extreamity, the earth riued, and was torne vp by reaſon of the hollownes therof, vnder the which they were incloſed &amp; ſmothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to death, from the like ſodaine end good Lord kéepe vs.</p>
            <p>It is alſo known for certainty, that néere vnto the Towne of Cauſeby in Oxford-ſhire, a little before Chriſtmas laſt, two young ſchollars comming from ſchoole the ſonnes of a wealthy Yeoman there dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, were by theſe terrible tempeſts both blown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſaw-pit, (by reaſon of this wet winter filled vp with durt and water) and there moſt lamentably drowned and choaked to death: oh wofull and piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hearing! eſpecially for the Parents of children, and ſuch as haue the tender féeling of loue and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that two ſweet boies brought vp by coſt and care, ſhould be thus and in this manner caſt away.</p>
            <p>Another ſorrowfull relation, muſt I here preſent vnto your hearing, which hapned in the Eaſterne
<pb facs="tcp:3468:8"/> parts of Northhampton-ſhire, of a wind-mil, which as well by the negligence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Miller, as the violent force of the wind, cauſing the mill ſayles to exceede their vſuall ſwiftnes, was thereby (wanting graine to grind) by the Mil-ſtones ſet on fire, being in the night, the flakes and ſparkles thereof by the fierce windes were blowne a long mile off, (as it pleaſed God) quight ouer a Village vnto a ricke of peaſe, where fetting the ſame on fire it was ſodainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, with fifty fat Weathers feeding thereat; the rage and extreamity of theſe two great oppreſſors, the Fire and the Winde, ſo preuailed, that not one man durſt aduenture the ſauing therof; and I haue heard it reported by diuers in that Countrey that the conſumed Rick and ſhéep, belonged to an extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting rent-racker, a raiſer of cheape markets, and a hoarder vp of corne from poore people: here was the powerfull hand of God ſhowne, Heauen herein was iuſt, which would not let ſuch wicked déeds go vnpuniſhed; God grant that hereby all the like do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers may take example, and turne their hearts, that they may bee mercifull to them that ſtand in neede.</p>
            <p>Turne now but our eyes more nearer London, &amp; wée may behold the hand of Heauen lifted againſt vs many waies, yea manie waies by theſe laſt guſts of windy tempeſts for our wickednes, as by trees torne vp by the roots, ſtanding before in all winds &amp; weathers ſafe and found for theſe two hundred yéers paſt.</p>
            <p>Alſo, the noble City of London it ſelfe can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes much hurt that is come thereby, as diuers peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſore bruiſed and maimed by falls of chimnies, corners and ſides of houſes, the blowing downe of tyles and ſuch like.</p>
            <p>The very Riuer of Thames, is alſo a preſident
<pb facs="tcp:3468:8"/> hereof, where by the rigorous ſtrength of the windes the water (with the tyde flowing ouer-fiercely) made a moſt dangerous breach ouer the banks into the Medowes &amp; Marſhes by Stratford le bow, &amp; Ham, where many thouſand akers of faire grounds are quite ouer-flowne and drowned, to the great hurt and hindrance of many the Inhabitants of London, as thoſe Townes therabouts, the recouery wherof, by men of ſuch vnderſtanding, wil coſt much time, with inualuable ſums of money, to the great griefe and care of many hundreds.</p>
            <p>The like hindrance though not in that kinde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell vnto diuers Citizens of London in October laſt, of whom I know ſome now dwelling in S. Sepulchers pariſh without New-gate, whoſe names for good cauſe I omit, who being at Sitting-borne faire in Kent, where diſpatching their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſending their goods and wares vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards London in a ſmall Bark or Ship, were moſt lamentably ſunke and caſt away in the reach ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Barking in Eſſex.</p>
            <p>In the ſame County of Eſſex, at Ilford where a Gentlemans houſe ſtandeth brauely built with a high turret leaded ouer, had the log and leads ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on blowne off, and by the windes turnd vp into a round role, which to all mens reaſon may ſeeme ſtrange, that the windes ſhould bee of ſo great a force to remoue ſo waighty a ſubſtance, as that met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle is knowne to be of.</p>
            <p>From hence, if wee but hearken downe to the Sea ſide, and at moſt of our coaſt Townes, wee ſhall heare no other reports but of ſhipwracks and of drowned people in great numbers taken vp, and as it is verefied by ſome of great credit, that at one coaſt Towne of England, there hath beene at one certaine time a whole Cart-loade of drowned
<pb facs="tcp:3468:9"/> men carryed from the Sea ſide.</p>
            <p>Oh wofull hearing! oh heauy and ſad ſpectacle! it euen ſtrikes my very ſoule with feare to tell it; in many places where I haue béen I haue heard bitter complaints made, ſome by fathers for their loſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſome by children for their loſt fathers, which the ſea hath buried vp in watery granes, women for huſbands, brother for brother, and friend for friend; ſorrow is on euery ſide, and all wrought by theſe late outragious tempeſts, neuer the like in this our ſinfull age of the world.</p>
            <p>But againe to our purpoſe, another accident comes to my mind, which is requiſite and fit to bee reported for the ſtrangeneſſe thereof, for it begets cauſe of heauines; a certaine ſhip of London, laden with rich commodities of diuers Merchants of this honorable City, making for the Eaſt countries, and ſetting forth before Michalmas laſt, hath euer ſince (by tempeſtuous and croſſe windes) béene toſſed vp and downe the narrow ſeas, ſome time vpon one coaſt, ſomtime vpon another, ſtill driuen from place to place in great danger, no way able (by reaſon of contrarie gales) to finiſh their intended voiage, but are now at laſt caſt backe vpon our owne ſhoare, where the Owners are forced againe to re-victuall their ſhip, to their great loſſe and hindrance; a charge lying too heauie vpon ſome mens backs, but God is mercifull, and ſendeth theſe afflictions to try the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of his ſeruants, whoſe loſſes no doubt but he will reſtore with a three folde increaſe of plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full bleſſings.</p>
            <p>Thus by degrees do we enter into wo, after wo, where the reports of one miſhap, ſtill prooues an induction to another, either of dangers by ſea, or loſſes vpon land, which I am heare bound vpon
<pb facs="tcp:3468:9"/> occaſion is intermingle, contrary to true method in writing, but not to be tedious, this muſt I certifie you of, that there is intelligeces vpon the exchange among Marchants, of the ouerflowing &amp; drowning of townes in the Low-countries, where many hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds haue periſhed in their owne houſes, by the merciles ſeas, driuen in by theſe late windes, oh heart breaking newes: eſpecially to that country people there borne, and here dwelling in <hi>London,</hi> in this ſodaine manner to heare of the ſad farwel of their friends and kindred, thus to looſe their deare liues.</p>
            <p>It is certefied likewiſe that the famous City of <hi>Antwerpe</hi> that floure of <hi>Brabant</hi> for famous buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings hath had great ſpoiles by this wind and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and that part of that worthy city is ouerflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereby, to the impoueriſhing of diuers Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, whoſe factors be here reſident in <hi>England,</hi> but becauſe forraine reports doe not much concerne our diſcourſes, we wil fil vp this our volume with our home bred caſualties.</p>
            <p>The towne of <hi>Douer</hi> here in <hi>Kent,</hi> can wel declare the powerful ſtrength of theſe Winter winds, where from time to time, is vioiently caſt out of the ſeas whole ſhelues and heapes of ſand and ſtone, with many other things to the great wonder of the inhabitants: thoſe that durſt aduenture to ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſhoare ſide, in the fulneſſe of any of theſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, did behold ſtrange battles, betwixt the wind and waters, where as it ſéemed, waues like moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, danſt in the ſkies,<note place="margin">T.</note> and the whole ſeas appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red like a fiery world, al ſparkling red, ſuch was it, and ſo terrible, that it euen frighted the carefull ſhipmen, to looke aboue hatches.</p>
            <p>The county of <hi>Kent</hi> hath borne a pittiful ſhare of theſe late wracked ſpoiles, and hath receiued as
<pb facs="tcp:3468:10"/> much loſſe as any one country beſide: amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other hurts there happened, this one here follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wil I make knowne as a thing both ſtrange and feareful. About ſome foure miles from Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, at a towne called Great Chart, vpon Saint Iohns day laſt, being Sunday, in the time of Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning prayer, the Church being full of people, aroſe a moſt terrible tempeſt of lightning, wind, and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, raging extreamly, to the great affright of man, woman and child there remayning, in the middeſt of which feare, broake into the Church a moſt vgly ſhape out of the ayer like vnto a broad eyd bul,<note place="margin">T.</note> and daſht the Miniſters booke out of his hand, with which blow the ſame arme and hand was ſtroken lame and black, whereupon the whole audience ſo fearefully preſſed one vpon another to get forth that many were hurt and almoſt bruzed to death, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which number a Millor was quite ſlaine, by the fright of this miſhapen ſpirit, for ſo was it thought to be, which without doing further hurte vaniſhed away, taking with it a part of the Church wal, leauing the whole aſſembly lying almoſt ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered one vpon anothers back. It is not for vs mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, to iudge the euent hereof, but this is reported of the ſame towne of Chart, the pariſhioners haue an euil cuſtome among them, for continually, be it either in ſeruice or ſermon time, they wil ſtand in troupes of foure or fiue in a company in diuers parts of the Church, conferring &amp; talking of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affaiers, not regarding at al the words of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, but rather behaue themſelues as it were in a faier or market, to the great griefe of each well diſpoſed Chriſtian, preparing himſelf to the ſeruice of Almighty God, vnder whoſe ſhield we ought to make our defence againſt the temptations of the Prince of darkeneſſe. And now to draw nere vnto
<pb facs="tcp:3468:10"/> a concluſion, I thinke it not impertinent, nor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting to ad vnto theſe our feareful diſcourſes in like maner a terrible tempeſt of wind and thunder that happened néere vnto the towne of Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham as it is recorded by <hi>I. S.</hi> a Citizen of London, and knowne for a troth of the inhabitants there now. This marueilous tempeſt in great fury, the wind outragiouſly blowing, came thundering tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough two townes, and beate downe many houſes with part of both the Churches, the one of them a vilage nere vnto the foreſaid towne of Nottingham called Sueton adioyning to the Riuer of Trent, which had their bels caſt to the out-ſide of the Church-yard, and ſome webs of lead foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred foote into the field writhen like vnto a paier of gloues: the Riuer of Trent running betwéene the two townes, had the water with the mud in the bottom carried a quarter of a mile, and caſt againſt trees, and the trees torne vp by the rootes, and caſt twelue ſcore off: alſo a child was taken foorth of a mans hand two ſpeares length high, carryed a hundred foote from him, and then let fall, and ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: alſo fiue or ſixe men therabout dyed by this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt: God be mercifull and grant vs patience in ſuch like extremities, many other ſtrange accidents there hapned as then, of the truth wherof let no man doubt, for of the ſame there is ſufficient proofe, and will be verefied, if occaſion ſerue, God with his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched arme defend and keepe vs from the like death as many vnhappely haue here in our Country both by ſea and land taſted, and grant that wee may ſeriouſly to our owne goods beare in remembraunce all theſe forepaſſed reports, that they may put vs in minde to ſhunne the wayes of the wicked, for all theſe related calamities
<pb facs="tcp:3468:11"/> haue béene laied vpon vs for our ſinnes, we ſée how our good Father is loath to chide vs too firce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and vnwilling to ſtrike vn too terribly, therefore let theſe paſſed warnings mooue vs to good life, which God for his choſen ſake grant. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3468:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
